Hi.
In this project, we're going to building a
to-do list application
called Odot, which if you can't already
tell, is to-do backwards.
Super creative.
We're gonna be using Ruby and Ruby on
Rails version 4.0 to get this all going.
This app is gonna be pretty simple to
start with.
We're going to create to do lists, add
items to them and mark them as complete.
As we're coding this application,
we're gonna be writing automated tests
alongside it.
Automated tests are programs that work
alongside our code to make
sure that our code does what we expect it
to do.
The tools that we're going to be using to
write this automated tests are called
r-spec and cucumber.
If you haven't already, you'll need to
follow the setting up
a Ruby development environment videos, in
order to get a ruby and
ruby on rails development environment set
up.
We will be using the Ruby on Rails
virtual machine to work through everything
in this project.
So let's go ahead and get started.
Okay, so let's get started and build our
Rails app.
I'm going to assume that you have Ruby and
Ruby On Rails installed.
If not, go on over and check
out the installing a Ruby development
environment series.
In there we show you how to get up and
running with Ruby and Ruby On Rails.
Now in this particular screen cast, we're
going to
be using the Tree house Virtual Machine to
code along.
And I'll make sure to mark where you do
not need to type out
certain things if you are not using
the virtual machine and you've installed
everything locally.
So let's go ahead and get started.
Now I've launched a terminal here in OS
10.
If you're
on Windows, you can launch a command
prompt but again, I'm
going to be assuming that we're working
with the virtual machine.
So I have the virtual machine folder set
up
in Treehouse, so I'm gonna change to the
Treehouse directory.
And type Vagrant Up.
Vagrant Up is going to initialize and boot
the virtual machine and then it'll be
able to get started.
Okay, now that that is initialized.
We type vagrant ssh and we will be in.
These two steps, you can ignore if you are
not using the virtual machine.
Okay.
Now, lets change to our projects directory
and we can go ahead and
generate our Rails application.
Now, we are building a to do list
application.
Lets call it, odot which is to do
backwards.
Isn't that clever?
So type rails new odot.
And then Rails is going to go through and
do a bunch of things for us.
Right now it's creating a skeleton Rails
app,
basically a blank Ruby on Rails
application, and
installing certain things inside of it.
So now that that's generated, let's type
cd odot.
Okay here we are.
Now I'm gonna go ahead and launch sublime
text two.
And we'll take a look around, see what
Rail's generated for us.
Okay, so Sublime has launched, and I'm
going to click File and Open.
So here is my home folder And I have the
Treehouse Virtual Machine
in the Treehouse folder so I double click
that and projects and here is odot.
So I'm gonna open that up.
Now even though I'm in the virtual machine
anything that is
in that projects folder gets shared so I
can access it locally.
So here's the Rails app that was generated
for us.
Right now, using the latest version of
Ruby On Rails,
so that's 4.0.1 as of the time of this
recording.
As long as the first two numbers are 4.0
we'll
be good to go here and you can follow
along.
If it's 4.1 there may be some differences,
and
go ahead and ask for help on the forum.
So this is something called the Gem file.
This is generated by default in all Ruby
on Rails applications.
And it contains
all of the different libraries that we're
using.
It uses another gem called Bundler to
manage all of these dependencies.
So what it will do is lock these
particular versions to our application.
Now over on the left, we have a bunch of
different directories.
We have app, bing, config, and so on.
This is where all of our application files
go.
The app directory contains applications
specific code.
So the assets directory contains our
images, Javascript and style sheets.
These use the Rails asset pipeline.
Which means that Rails is going to
generate all this for us on deployment.
Now we don't have to worry about that just
yet,
but we'll go through later as we get into
it.
Next up we have the controllers directory.
The controllers directory contains all
of the controllers for our application.
One thing we get by default is the
application controller, and
that is going to be the core controller of
the application.
For the most part, all of our other
controllers are
going to do something called inherit from
the application controller.
Which means that they get all of
the different methods from the application
controller.
So if we want
something to be in every single controller
on our site, certain
piece of behavior, we would put it in the
application controller.
Now, in Ruby terms, this less than means
it inherits from something.
So, we can see the application controller
inherits from action controller and this
base call.
We don't need to worry about that right
now but we'll get into it
at some point.
Helpers contain view helpers for the
application.
Now, as we go through and generate
different parts of our
application, what we'll be generating soon
is a to do list.
Each particular piece of code that we
generate will get its own helper.
If we want something, a certain piece of
behavior to apply to all of our different
views, we will put that in the application
helper.
Now, for the most part, helpers are going
to be used to generate code for our views.
While, controller code would be used to
generate behavior for our controllers.
Mailers contained different mailers for
our application.
So, if we wanna make a to-do list mailer.
Get mails out our to-do list of people.
That will go in the mailer's directory.
Right now it's empty.
We have this dot key file, which is there
in case
we check this into version control using
get, which we will do.
Our model's directly will contain all our
different models.
Concerns directory contains something
called concerns.
Which is going to be shared behavior
between models.
And our views directory
contains the layouts for our application.
Rails generates a default layout for us,
which it stores in the
application.html.erb template.
And as you can see, it looks like basic
HTML, but there are some differences here.
We've got the style sheet link tag,
these JavaScript link tags, and different
code there.
When you see these tags right here, the
less
than, percent, and equals.
That means it's calling a helper, or
evaluating some sort
of code, and then displaying the results
of the code.
Now if you didn't see the equal sign, that
means
that the output of the code would not be
there.
It would simply be evaluated inside the
context of the template.
If you ever run into an issue where you
can't figure
out why you are not able to see certain
code.
It might be because you don't have the
equal size.
Now, we'll see a little bit later some of
the differences
between the two but for now, I am gonna
move on.
The bin directory contains different
programmatic
functions that we'll use with Rails.
Now when just generator our rails
application
we used the Rails command to do
so, inside of the bin directory, we
get commands that are specific to our
application.
And as we go through, and code our
application, we will be able to modify
this.
Close these here.
Our config directory contains different
configuration for our application.
Now the routes file, this is all commented
out right now.
But this is where we tell our application
where different parts go.
So let's say we wanted to go to our
application slash to do lists.
We would put that directive inside the
routes.rb file.
Inside of the config directory as well is
something called our database.yml file.
This contains our database configuration
for each environment.
When we start out coding a Rails
application, we start out in the
development environment.
And we can see development is configured
right here.
It's using the sqlite3 adapter, and it's
saying the database is actually
a file, in the db directory right here,
called development.sqlite3.
Now, you'll notice that that file does not
exist yet.
And the reason is, we don't have anything,
we didn't generate it.
But, we'll go through and do that shortly.
We also have this
config/application.rb.
The application configuration contains
very specific configuration code, for our
application.
And this is going to be, for global
settings in our application.
Now, if we wanted to have specific
settings that
came with plugins, we could put them in
initializers.
Now we do have some configuration options
that are commented out for us.
This is where you can do things like add
to the
load path, change the time zone, and a
bunch of different stuff.
We can check out the Rails documentation
for more configuration options.
For the most part we're not gonna need to
worry about it right now.
And as I said before we have different
environments which we configured here.
We can even do further configuration
environmentally specifically.
Now, all of these different options we
have
in the development environment right here.
We could put in the application
configuration, if
we wanted them to apply to every
environment.
In general, we want to keep these as
environmentally specific as possible.
Now one more thing, the locales directory
contains translation information.
So, if we wanted to translate our
application into another language,
we would have the translation keys right
here, and then if we
wanted to translate, we would call this
I18n method .T and hello.
And then if
we were using a different locale we would
call it like this.
And we can define all of that in here.
We're not gonna worry about that in this
project.
Okay, so we'll close the config directory.
The lib directory contains different
library code for our application.
And that is application specific.
So if we have written a different time
library or something
crazy like that we could keep that in the
lib directory.
It also contains tasks.
These are rate tasks which work with our
application.
Not something we're going to need to worry
about right now.
Our log directory contains the logs to our
application
which is going to be very useful when
debugging.
Now we haven't started this application
just yet.
But once we do, we will see a log, and
then since we're in the development
environment, we would see development.log.
If we were in the test or production
environments,
we would have similarly named files as
well, per environment.
The public directory contains a few
different files right now.
This is our 404, 422, and 500 pages, in
case there are errors, or a file is not
found.
So here is the default 500 page when
there's an error in the application.
You can see the CSS is right in line.
The reason that these are static files is
so that we don't have to worry about any
other application code running if we have
already have an issue.
Now, it used to be previous versions of
Rails,
we would have public images, JavaScripts
and style sheets.
If you are using the asset pipeline, you
don't need to worry about that.
You wanna put your applicaiton in specific
assets like JavaScripts and all that.
Right here inside the app assets directory
and then we call them later.
Finally we have this test directory.
We're not going to be using test unit in
this project.
We're going to be using something called
rspec to do our testing.
Testing is a pretty important of Rails and
we'll see how to do that later.
And for right now, that's about all we
need to
worry about, so that's a little walk
through of the application.
Now let's go ahead and make sure that this
runs.
So, the way we do that is by calling Rails
server.
So I'm going to clear my screen right
here, [SOUND] and type bin/rails because
we're wanting to use the specific Rails
tied to our application, and then server.
Okay, so once the Rail server is running,
we can get to that by
opening up our web browser.
I'm using Chrome here, but any web browser
will do.
And we can go to localhost port 3,000.
Okay, this looks good.
We're riding ruby on rails.
In our next screen cast, what we're gonna
do is generate our to-do
list scaffold and start working with it.